this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello this is Matthew Farwell
for software engineering radio today's
episode is about web assembly with Alan
Clark
Lynne Clark makes code cartoons she's
also part of Mozilla's emerging
technologies group while she works with
a web assembly and Rusted teams her
current project is making it easy to use
web assembly with today's JavaScript
tools including NPM and bundlers in
previous lives she worked at NPM and she
was a core contributor to open source
projects like Firefox is developer tools
and contributed to HTML data standards
welcome to software engineering radio
Lynn thank you so much for inviting me
to be on here okay today we're going to
talk about web assembly we've covered
web application development with
JavaScript in the past for instance in
episode 293 Yakov a non angular web
assembly is a new technology for
creating what web applications so Lynn
what are the goals of web assembly well
one of the big goals of web assembly is
to make it possible to have consistent
performance in your applications
so you know traditionally you have three
languages that you use when you're
building a web page you have HTML 4
giving the structure to the page you
have CSS for styling it and then you
have JavaScript for adding behaviors
okay and you know if you want to have an
application that runs performant ly in
JavaScript you can do that for most web
applications but if can sometimes
javascript wasn't really designed to be
fast it was designed to be easy to get
up and running with it quickly and there
are some things in JavaScript that make
it hard for the browser's to actually
run JavaScript quickly so what web
assembly does is give you a language
that can do a lot of the same things as
JavaScript that can give you those
behaviors on your page
interactivity but can do so in a more
consistently performant way and the way
that it does this is by giving the
programmer a little bit more control
over exactly how the code runs so for
example how your code works with memory
okay so what do the target use cases
then if you're saying it's a performance
based thing the original target use case
the first one that we worked on was for
PC games because when you're playing PC
games if you were to have a PC game that
used JavaScript you might have GC pauses
you might have places where the code was
a little bit inefficient and so you'd
have that game dropping frames so you'd
have gaps in the animation it would
really kind of take you out of the
experience of playing that game so web
assembly we originally partnered with
game companies like unity the Unreal
Engine those kinds of game development
tools so that they could target the web
as a platform okay so is it just full
visualization or is it for other things
as well that was the original use case
but now you're seeing it being used in
other use cases as well so for example
Adobe has their Lightroom product which
can run on the web it's an image editor
AutoCAD has a lightweight CAD editor
that can run on the web I think it's
called for MIT so you're seeing these
kinds of applications that you would
previously have to install directly on
your computer now it's possible to run
them in the browser itself so that you
don't need to install anything you can
just download it on the web right there
from the URL and it'll be there in your
browser we also are seeing some other
use cases for example the parse the
source map library that's used in tools
like web pack one of the the maintainer
of that is on our team at Mozilla and he
decided to take the parsing and querying
part of the source map library and
convert that to web assembly from
JavaScript
he saw six times a speed increase for
that part of the code ember is also
working
with taking the bytecode interpreter
they have the glimmer bytecode
interpreter that they've been working on
and rewriting that in rust that will
compile to web assembly and so it's both
these applications these full-fledged
applications that would normally be
developed in languages like C and C++
and also these smaller parts of
applications where you can see the
performance improvements from web
assembly okay so that's a good question
who is behind web assembly who's pushing
it all for browser vendors have gotten
on board we started this thing called
azzam jeaious at mozilla in 2012 or so
and that was the seed of this idea but
the folks that were behind us and jsn
particular one that i work with a lot
Luc Wagner did a really good job of
getting other people on board at the
same time Google had this project called
pinnacle that had a lot of the same aims
and so through meetings with Google and
with other companies Microsoft and and
with the JSC team at Apple they were
able to come up with a common vision and
that's really how web assembly started
is this common vision across all of the
browsers for how you can have this more
consistently performant code that runs
on the web okay so as I understand it
web assembly was based on Azam Jas
could you explain a bit more about azzam
Jas and a little bit about the history
sure hassan jessica has an interesting
history so we had a an engineer at
Mozilla who had come up with this tool
called him script in which you could use
to take code that was written in C or
C++ and compile it to JavaScript but
that code ran really slowly so we had
folks at Mozilla that wanted to make it
run faster they put together some
engineers in a room Luke has a great
story about how he when he first looked
at what inscription was doing he's that
there's no way you can make this fast
but then came up with this idea for how
you could have a little signal to the
JavaScript engine what types it was
working with and with that you can make
as MJS
you know the the code that this M
scripting compiler was spitting out you
could actually make it possible to
optimize it in the JavaScript engine so
really as I'm Jess was just a strict
subset of JavaScript that used a couple
of kind of weird conventions to make it
possible for the engine to run that
JavaScript quickly and and it wasn't
until they started working on web
assembly that you move to something that
wasn't actually JavaScript okay so as I
if I understand you correctly as I'm
Jess this is a subset of JavaScript
which is can be seen by the compiler in
Firefox and it picks that up and runs it
fast
exactly okay so the question is why why
do we need web assembly why can't we
just make JavaScript faster what well
there are certain things about
JavaScript that that do make it hard to
make it fast that dynamic types that you
have in JavaScript can make it really
hard to make it javascript is faster and
there are only so many shortcuts that
you can add to a JavaScript engine you
know there's only so many hacks another
problem is that even if you optimize to
a particular JavaScript engine because
these are all heuristics and hacks and
everything that you're putting into the
JavaScript engine to make the con road
code run fast if you optimize to one
JavaScript engine it could D optimize
your code for a different engine so run
slow in a different engine web assembly
you're going to have more consistent
performance not just across your
application running in one browser
you're also going to have more
consistent performance across all of the
browsers so what exactly is web assembly
what is it it is ok I talk about it as
if it's a language but really it's more
of a compiler target so when you're
working with web assembly you're going
to be writing in a language like C or
C++ or rust that compiles so web
assembly web assembly gives you you know
some a small set of operations like you
would have with an assembly language it
gives you the small set of operations
that you know your your higher-level
language can compile to but it's not
actually an assembly language it because
it's not targeting a particular physical
machine it's not targeting you know x86
or anything like that it is targeting a
conceptual machine I get shipped down to
the browser that's the browser takes it
from this slightly higher level assembly
down to the actual assembly for whatever
machine is running on ok so similar to
Java bytecode in a way yes ok so does
that mean that it's just a virtual
machine inside Firefox or in Chrome
exactly it's actually using the same VM
as the JavaScript engine it is in the
JavaScript engine implementing
JavaScript engine ok so web assembly is
is kind of an assembly language so do I
need to write in the assembly language
you mentioned C or C++ earlier on can I
write in C or C++ you can write in the
assembly language if you want to just
like other assembly languages you can't
write in them if you want to very very
few people actually want to can't write
their assembly so most people are going
to be using a compiler tool chain that
compiles to web assembly right now that
usually means C C++ or rust that's
because those languages for the web
assembly MVP the web assembly that's in
browsers right now they're more well
suited to it
because the web assembly MVP didn't have
garbage collection support so you want
to have languages that like C and C++
where you're manually memory your map
managing your memory yourself using
malloc and free or rust has this these
concepts of ownership and borrowing that
make it so that the language can help
you clean up after yourself but either
way neither of them require garbage
collection we are accelerating the
garbage collection proposal through the
web assembly standards group so soon you
will be able to integrate an interrupt
with the browser's built-in garbage
collection and
we'll open doors to a whole bunch of
other languages make it so that they can
work with web simply in an optimal way
because right now you can't ship down
your own garbage collector but that's
inefficient for a number of reasons
you're adding bytes to your awasum file
you know it's running slightly slower
than it would be the built-in GC that
you have in browsers has just been so
highly tuned and optimized that really
makes a lot more sense just to use that
built-in browser GC I have no desire to
write a garbage collector okay so I'm
slightly confused about what we actually
do to use web assemblies so if I were to
use let's imagine do I do I need to
write a main function or good question
so what you get when you compile web
assembly is you get a dot wasm lot file
and that gives you a module so when
you're working with web sembly you're
always working with modules and those
modules provide functions they provide
functions that JavaScript code can use
and that web assembly code can use so
javascript actually boots up your web
assembly for you right now we have we
only have for creating these modules you
have to use an imperative JavaScript API
to actually fetch the file instantiate
it give it its imports that kind of
stuff we are working on making it so
that you can have a declarative module
API you can use a declarative module API
like Java scripts ES module in fact the
same API as Java scripts yes module API
and then you'll be able to use web
assembly modules and JavaScript modules
in the same module graph easily as if
the web assembly were JavaScript but for
now what you're doing is you're booting
up this module in your JavaScript and
then using javascript javascript to
control the you know call functions from
web assembly that kind of stuff
okay so effectively your functions that
declare are available from JavaScript
and the JavaScript engine just makes
them available so if you export them yes
okay so what can I do in a function can
let's let's take it let's take an
example for our hello
I want to do a printf not let's make it
a bit simpler than that
I just want to return a string can I
return a string and it's available in
JavaScript so that does get a little
tricky right now the only types that
webassembly understands natively are
integers and floats and so you can't
really pass strings back and forth
between javascript and web assembly what
you have to do is if you have a string
let's say that you want it to pass a
string from JavaScript into web assembly
you would take that string and use the
text encoder API to convert the string
into numbers and then you would put
those numbers into web assemblies and
memory object so this memory object it
basically emulates a heap you can put
bytes into it it's an it's an array
buffer javascript has this concept of an
array buffer which is an array of bytes
so you put those numbers into this array
and then you pass the index of the first
character over to webassembly
as if it were a pointer okay so that's
how you work with web assemblies
basically passing in more complex types
currently there are proposals to make
this easier and there are also tools
that make this easier so one of the
tools that we're working on is called
wasm lines gen and that will wrap your
code it will take a look at what your
signature is and it will wrap your web
assembly function with JavaScript code
that can actually do you know take the
bytes put them into memory for you or
encode the string put the bytes into
memory you pass the pointer do all that
for you right now that is specific to
rust but it's architected in a way where
we'd be able to add support for other
languages like C and C++ just that just
as an aside does that imply that you
need a static type do you need a type
definition yes okay yes basically one of
the things about web assembly that makes
it different from JavaScript is that you
are working with static types and so
that makes it so that the engine doesn't
have to guess at your types and doesn't
have to monitor your code to see what
types you're using and then
make guesses possibly wrong guesses
about what those types are so it's very
much a C or C++ model not a JavaScript
model exactly okay
another interesting question would be
okay so I mentioned printf earlier on
okay so do I need to write all my own
functions so imagine I wanted to take
the power of two two numbers mm-hmm
where does that power function come from
so one of the proposals that is in the
works right now is called the host
bindings proposal and that would make it
possible for you to basically work with
Dom objects and if you have anything a
JavaScript object or a Dom object where
you can call a method on it that would
do that kind of work you'll be able to
call those directly from web sembly
right now you can't do that directly you
can pass in functions that can do that
you can pass in JavaScript functions
that can do whatever you need to do but
you can't call the Dom objects methods
directly from web assembly could you
just explain quickly what the DOM is
sure so the Dom are the set of objects
in the browser that represents
everything on a web page so a paragraph
will have a Dom object a div will have a
Dom object but you also have other api's
that are available via Dom objects so
the math object those will be available
directly to webassembly eventually
eventually but not not at the minute you
have to do some mucking around okay yeah
so does that apply to let's call them
system calls because I don't know how
you would describe that so for in for
instance things which talk to the
network so one one example that I think
of a lot is a file system and and the
reason why that one is particularly
interesting is because you really don't
want your browser to have direct access
to the file system so in those cases you
can use libraries that will emulate so
for the file system you can emulate a
file system in index DP in the browser
script in will help with that if you're
using code and see that requires the
file system you can base
we use some scripting to add some code
to emulate that okay so it's another
interesting question is is how much of a
Sun books do we have are you in a Sun
books when you talk yes you're in
basically the same sandbox that you're
in for JavaScript that's one of the neat
things about using the JavaScript engine
using this existing VM is that VM has
been really hardened because it's one of
the most attacked pieces of code that we
have and so by running web assembly in
that same VM we're getting a lot of the
same protections a lot of the same
thought that's been put into JavaScript
security will then apply to web assembly
okay can I use third-party libraries
like boost for instance I am not
familiar with boost boost is a CEO C++
library I'm not quite sure which
standard library functions for instance
mmm I to be honest I don't know all that
one okay you mentioned malloc and free
could you explain what that is and how
you would use them in the context of web
assembly sure you know when you're
working with a C or C++ you're going to
be actually managing your memory
yourself you're going to be allocating
memory and then when you're done with it
you're going to free that memory the way
that that works for web assembly is
you're allocating memory inside of that
array buffer that memory object and then
you're freeing the memory inside of that
array buffer but having it limited to
that array buffer is actually pretty
nice because it gives you isolation
between different modules so if a
different module is you know doesn't
know what it's doing as far as smell
looking and freeing it's not going to
impact your module it will stay in its
own little own little box of memory and
there are some security considerations
around that too that make the web sembly
memory a lot more secure than most
people think would be okay well we'll do
security on it in a minute I'm going to
come on to that just to clarify so each
module has its own sandbox
let's call it yeah basically each module
gets its own memory there is some vision
in the future that you would be able to
share memories between modules but
that's not currently part of this back
okay can I allocate a lot of memory in
that module so you when you're setting
up your web assembly module you say how
many pages of memory you want in your
memory object and you can grow that
memory object later if you need more
memory so you could theoretically just
get more and more and more and more and
more mm-hmm
okay so when you say pages do you mean
an operating system-level page or a web
page for the allocation of public for
the allocation when you're um saying how
large you want your memory object to be
that is specified I think it's 64
kilobytes or something like that it's a
pretty granular level and you just say
how many of those you want your how big
you want your array buffer to be based
on that size is that fixed the size of a
single page is fixed but you can say how
many pages you want so multiples of that
amount okay so let's move on to the how
you interact with the browser do I have
access to the Dom from webassembly no
you don't yet but we are working on the
hosts bindings proposal that I mentioned
before will give you that direct Dom
access so that will make it possible for
you to create and pass around and
manipulate these Dom objects from
webassembly directly but I have to pass
if I want them to be manipulated then I
have to pass them in for now once the
host bindings proposal is there you'll
be able to create them within web
assembly I to be honest I am NOT as
involved in that proposal as I am in
other proposal so I don't know the the
exact future of it but at least from
what their plans are you would be able
to create a Dom object in your web
assembly code but surely that means that
if your web module can access that Dom
object or do you have to copy the you
have to physically copy the bytes over
to that into the memory for the web as
them for the module no you don't there's
these things called tables that can hold
references there's a proposal going
through right now that the host bindings
proposal depends on called
any reference that would allow you to
have references to objects that are not
inside your linear memory okay so I can
access that memory but I can't overwrite
it
exactly yeah you can basically you can
you can get a pointer to that object but
you can't actually write a new memory
address for it or anything like that
so to recap if I want my webassembly
module to access something which is
outside of its memory then I need to
copy it into one of these tables it's
not a as far as I'm understand it's not
a copy operation but yeah you get a
pointer and that's put in the table yeah
so theoretically I can escape my sandbox
you wouldn't really be escaping the
sandbox it would only be giving you the
same access that JavaScript has to those
objects okay because the webassembly
can't actually feed the values in those
tables it can just say I want to use the
object that's in this array index of the
table oh okay right and how do I access
the network kind of make Ajax calls for
instance not directly from webassembly
at the moment so the fetch API is what a
lot of people are using right now once
we have the direct access to the Dom you
can use the fetch API and the way that
you'd be able to use other api's but at
the moment there's webassembly is fairly
limited and that it can't actually reach
out to those api's and you mentioned
earlier on about garbage and creating
garbage collectable objects that's on
the roadmap but it's not exactly it's
not exactly possible at the minute right
yeah okay can I do multi-threading can I
do parallel operations right
the multi-threading story is it's a
little bit more of a complicated topic
than it was expected to be that's
because we wanted to have shared memory
multi-day so where you have multiple
threads that are sharing the same bit of
memory and this was going to be possible
and fairly straightforward using shared
array buffers but unfortunately because
of Spector we had to disable shared rate
buffers in all of the browsers not just
Firefox but all of them have we're
optimistic that we're going to be able
to turn to your Dre buffers back on in
the browsers that we'll be able to find
a mitigate
for the security concerns around them
and once that happens it should be
pretty straightforward to introduce
support for shared memory multi but
because a lot of the work has actually
already been done for that before we
knew that we had to turn off share very
buffers but it will depend on getting
those turned back on Spectre is Spectre
is this bug that meltdown inspector are
the big bugs that came out in January
that processors have where their
speculation basically made it possible
for you to access parts of memory that
you really theoretically should not have
access to and shared array buffers so
one of the it's it's called a timing
attack and shared array buffers could be
used to create a timer that could assist
this timing attack okay
the high resolution timer is what
they're called okay so can I use other
JavaScript libraries can I do coals from
webaim's webassembly back into the
JavaScript so you can pass in functions
there are these things called function
imports you can pass in functions from
JavaScript and then called those
JavaScript functions but that's one of
those cases where you actually need to
know what you want to call you need to
know what you're passing into your
module you don't have access willy-nilly
to everything in JavaScript at this
point so as a development model in my
head I'm thinking this is more of a
functional style approach because you're
passing everything into something and
then you're just getting an answer out
at the end is that kind of well your web
assembly module can maintain state so I
don't know if I would consider it
functional in that way because you you
know you are maintaining some state in
your memory object okay
does web assembly work on mobile
browsers it does yes one of the again
one of the nice things about
implementing it inside of the the VM
that's already in browsers is that it
makes it relatively easy to turn it on
in mobile browsers so I believe that all
of now unfortunately as part of the
mitigation of the specter bug Apple
broke
there I Oh s support for webassembly
that I think is still ongoing they're
fixed for that so on iOS devices web
assemblies a little wonky right now but
theoretically there's nothing that that
holds us back from having web assembly
across all mobile devices okay what what
is the ecosystem like for web assembly
what has been compiled to web assembly
what is available in web assembly so
right now you have a lot of the early
libraries that have been made available
are around things like compression
things that are computationally
intensive but this is really early days
as far as libraries that are being
imported to web assembly made available
so we're just starting to see things
like as I was mentioning before the
source map library that's used in web
pack and other tools that being written
in web assembly and we expect a lot of
other libraries like that that are
widely used as kind of these you know
more utility libraries to have their
performance sensitive parts or even
rewritten and web assembly so it's not
another use case for web assembly
computationally intensive things
compression encryption exactly yes
you're seeing for example a lot of
interest from the blockchain folks
because that of course is
computationally intensive so these
computationally intensive tasks you can
just get much better performance from
web assembly I guess data visualization
as well drawing graphs mm-hmm yes yeah
there was a tool that I think the New
York Times released recently that used
web assembly for some pretty complex
data visualization okay so how long
before d3 gets rewritten in web assembly
great to see that cool is web assembly a
replacement for something like react
native I don't know if it's a
replacement for react native it could be
used by react native and I gave a talk
last year about what webassembly means
for react because you could actually
have something like the reconciliation
algorithm that
in react rewritten in something like
webassembly
and then it could be more easily reused
across these different projects but
cross react and react native so I don't
think of it as a competitor as much as
something that could end up actually
powering a project like react native and
you could even see I know that the
Facebook folks have been working a lot
on reason which is this language that is
more strictly typed as it's based on Oh
camel you could see that actually
compiling to web assembly that would be
a good way for you know react because
there's also a project that makes it
possible to react write react code and
reason you can see that potentially
moving moving react more towards web
assembly I guess I should have asked a
question what is react just a quick
summary so react is one of it's a
framework it's a JavaScript framework it
makes it possible for you to make web
applications and one of the neat things
about it is that it makes it possible
for you to say not here's point a in my
app here you know the user has an
interaction you want to get to point B
you don't have to say all of the steps
for how you get from point A to point B
you just say okay given that the user
has done this I want the app to be in
state B now here's what state B is react
you do all of the work to make that
happen okay and so the reconciliation
algorithm that I was talking about
before that you could rewrite in
webassembly
that's what figures out what changes
need to be made to go from point A to
point B and it would be possible for you
to do that in webassembly okay so the
changes that need to be made in the
webpage during the dome exactly okay
yeah react is Facebook yes it's it was
created at Facebook and it powers some
of their properties okay cool so moving
on to how I would develop in with web
assembly how does imagine that I'm web
application developer how does my
day-to-day development change so I think
that if you're just a you know web
developer you're not really working on
any really performance sensitive code
your day to day isn't going to change
very observably
probably start using libraries and
noticing that they're getting faster but
not you won't actually have to do
anything to see that speed improvement
you'll be just be downloading the
library that you use before and it will
just all of a sudden be faster but
you'll be using the same API to interact
with it
that's how we expect web assembly to
affect most you know average web
developers if you're working on one of
these libraries you know if you're
working on a react or something like
that then you may need to start
incorporating something languages that
compile to web assembly into your
toolbox but for most web developers they
won't even need to do anything ok so
imagine that I am working on one of
these sensitive applications where I've
got a dashboard or something like this
and I need to write stuff in webassembly
again how does my we I need to
incorporate C or C++ into my or you said
rust as well rust supported rust is
supported a lot of the work you know
validating awesome Jas and webassembly
happened with C and C++ code so that the
tool chain for those two languages is
more mature rust has just started
working on this over the past year
really so the tool chain isn't quite all
the way there but it is most of the way
there at this point could you envision
go the go project is actually currently
working on adding web assembly support
there's an issue where they're currently
working on it there are a few things
that make it slightly trickier for go
but yeah I definitely think that go
we'll be talking web assembly soon if I
was just working in JavaScript before I
need no need to work in JavaScript and
let's call it let's say C or C++ so I
need to have think in two languages
thinking two ways of thinking correct
although I think that you may see you
might see it because a lot of times when
you have those kinds of projects like a
reactor where an emperor that kind of
thing
you already have division of different
modules of different specializations I
think that you'll probably see that
these performance sensitive parts there
might already be boundaries between the
performance sensitive
and the people that are doing the other
parts of the application development of
the framework development and so it
would really be the the need for people
to learn another language would really
be concentrated in those areas and it
might be that you end up just hiring a
rust developer to do that work for you
who doesn't really know JavaScript super
well but who knows how to make the who
knows the algorithms and stuff that he
needs to make that stuff really fast and
so that person will then create those
modules because that's the great thing
about modules is they provide you these
boundaries that allow you to divide work
in this way that is actually one of the
reasons why modules were written the
1970s why modules were created was to
provide boundaries between people really
so you would have these people that
could do the the performance sensitive
code in a language like rust providing
an API that then JavaScript developers
could use but it's really a it's really
a separate mentality it's it's a
separate way of working it's a separate
way of thinking yes yeah I mean it
really is when you're developing a web
assembly module with rust you're really
developing a rust module that happens to
compile to web assembly and that could
happen to pop compile to other stuff too
you know you can you can use the same
module to compile to multiple targets
okay come on to that as well I have a
question about that later on okay so for
the C++ it's kind of a functional
thinking again is I have a I have a
function that I call and it returns a
value or not returns a value it's that
sort of okay so it's really a separate
API it's a separate module that's a
separate thing yes now one thing is that
when it returns a value you might need
to go into its memory to get the data
that is referring to okay
so can I do one of your interests is how
to use webpack and npm with the web
assembly could you explain a little bit
about what webpack is sure webpack is a
bundler so originally you weren't able
to use modules in the browser there was
there wasn't actually so you had modules
a node commonjs modules but you couldn't
use them
in the browser and then bundlers came
along and they basically emulated some
they took some of the runtime that you
would have in a project like note to
load modules and emulated that in the
browser so browserify is an early
example of this web pack has come along
since then web pack was developed so
that you could break these what browser
if I would do is it was it would create
one huge file that had all of your
modules in it and so it could be slow to
load because it needed to parse all of
those modules
you know evaluate them so web pack came
along to make it easier to split those
modules up across different files to do
this
chunking so what web pack gives you as a
way to load brow load modules in the
browser okay well we now have a way to
do that natively
yes modules have landed we are actually
turning them on in Firefox in our next
release and all of the other browsers
also have them on by default so you'll
be able to run these modules natively in
the browser so you might think that you
don't need a web pack anymore because
you don't need to have that extra bit of
code to run your modules but web pack
also gives you optimizations by taking
all these modules and putting them into
a single file
it makes for less HTTP traffic so you
have your waiting for less time for
things to download there are other
things that it does web pack is probably
still going to be used as an
optimization for people that are using
modules into the foreseeable future and
so we're working with web pack and with
other bundlers to make sure that we can
actually emulate this ES module support
that we're working on in the community
group in those bundlers as well okay a
question that I didn't ask earlier on is
how do we get these files into the
browser is it binary code or is it the
actual assembly so for web assembly yeah
you're downloading a binary file that
has binary code in it and you're
basically just fetching that file one of
the neat things that you can do with web
sembly is as each chunk of the file is
coming
over the network you can actually start
decoding and compiling it has that trunk
is coming in so you can do this thing
called streaming compilation as the you
know every line of binary code is coming
in it can be compiled okay so when use
webpack you can web pack actually has to
understand all of this web pack as I
understand it does three things it can
optimize the code as in it can cut out
bits of JavaScript that it's not using
and if there is a bit of JavaScript that
is never going to be cold then actually
when it bundles up into a single
JavaScript it actually removes that does
what is the idea that web pack would do
that as well for web assembly that's a
great question actually just in the past
month or so the maintainer of web pack
has started implementing that for web
assembly basically having dead code
elimination for web assembly as well as
JavaScript yes so that is one of the
things that you would that web pack
would do for you how much smaller are
the finals for web assembly than for
JavaScript it really depends because
sometimes you have code that actually is
takes more space when you are
representing it as simple instructions
so they can potentially be larger but a
lot of times they they can also be
smaller because binary representation is
just much more compact and it was
designed web simply was designed to be
compact so it is hard to say exactly
sometimes it'll be large or sometimes
it'll be smaller really depending on the
code so do the performance improvements
come from the fact that it doesn't have
to pass it on the way in there are a few
places where the performance
improvements come in so one of them is
that decoding with web symbol you don't
actually need to parse you just decode
it
so decoding is a lot faster than parsing
that's true and compiling you can do a
streaming compilation for us on Firefox
we can actually compile the code faster
than its coming in from the network so
basically as soon as you finish
downloading the bytes it will have
compiled all so you only need to
pilot once and a lot of the
optimizations that you need have been
done on the server side or you know
before you've gotten the code heat to
the browser so you don't need to do as
much optimization in the browser as you
would with JavaScript with JavaScript
you compile things multiple times if
they get used a lot you compile them
both with a baseline compiler and a
optimizing compiler with web assembly we
actually are doing that same work in
Firefox we do have a baseline compiler
and an optimizing compiler but the
optimizing compiler is running in the
background
sometimes with JavaScript you need to
recompile if you've if the JavaScript
engine made wrong incorrect guesses
about how your JavaScript works then it
will need to recompile the code based on
that on the fly so that's another place
where you spend time in JavaScript and
then there's garbage collection which is
only you know not an issue right now
because we don't have garbage collection
but eventually we will have garbage
collection okay so imagine that I'm
developing a web application
okay I'm using a module that's written
in this using web assembly when I'm
debugging what happens
what can I see in the console what can I
kind of evaluate expressions so the
bugging is currently web web assembly
debugging is kind of an open issue there
is some support for debugging and
browsers using the web assembly text
format but when you're debugging web
assembly you don't really want to be
looking directly at that text format you
don't really want to be looking directly
at the web assembly code you want to be
debugging the source language that you
wrote so if that's rust you would want
to be looking at rust code not the
actual web assembly that was compiled to
so then you could you need to source map
that's exactly yeah you know just as
JavaScript has minified you know you
have the minified javascript and then
you can use a source map to go from the
minified javascript back to the pretty
java script that you wrote you use a
source map to do that we have done some
experiments around that we've actually
been able to make rusts make it so that
you can debug rust that actually shows
up as rust code but through this
experimentation
that it wasn't clear that source maps
will actually give us everything that we
need and this is still an open question
that we're working on it's likely that
we're going to need to have more
substantial effort across different
browsers and different tool vendors to
make debugging webassembly a good
experience so you can actually find some
active work that's happening in the web
assembly community group and their
design repo and I'll send a link that
you can put in the show notes for that
or anything um yeah so does that mean
that I can step over I can step through
step in - yeah yeah and yeah you can
even when you're looking at the web
assembly text format yeah you can do
that stepping over and you'll see values
changing they're just values that it's
hard to ascribe meaning to as a human
programmer okay yes because it's just an
array buffer isn't it it's just an array
yeah you're just seeing you know you
might be seeing the local values and all
of that kind of stuff but it's really
kind of hard to read the web assembly
text format if you you know it's like
reading assembly code it's extremely
difficult to understand what's going on
okay cool are there any tools which help
you debug and not analyze web assembly
are there any static analysis tools so
yes there are a number of different
tools that people have created for doing
various things for example the
eliminating parts of the web assembly
file that you don't need that kind of
stuff I don't actually have a great list
of them right now but they're definitely
the because it you can statically
analyze web assembly there are tools
that have been created and one of the
nice things is that a lot of these tools
can work across different language
barriers okay what the place I'm coming
from it's okay so is C or C++ so imagine
that you want to call you you end up
calling a system call wish it wouldn't
be available in a browser
mmm on the web assembly org site the
demo is actually a unity 3d app called
tanks this was exported to web assembly
so I would imagine this was written in C
or C++ I don't know if you know that
offhand
[Music]
I don't know it offhand but let's let's
imagine that it was does this mean I can
have one single source code for the web
for Windows for Linux because it's all
in C++ yes that is the vision that they
started off with was yes
taking those code bases and just being
able to run them on the web without
having to do a bunch of extra work okay
so yes that's what all of the game
developers were saying too and that they
managed to actually get the demo event
working within two weeks right before
the game development conference and just
seeing that rapid progress how quickly
they were able to get from zero to
having something working having that
code working in the browser really wowed
the game developers and they were saying
yes cool
how does web assembly impact other
languages which are compiled to
JavaScript for instance closure scripts
college as typescript right can I change
the backend to generate web assembly
that is something that we're actively
talking with people right now so some of
the different languages that we've been
looking at our Elm would be a good
example of a language that could compile
to web assembly typescript so one of the
reasons why Elm is is a good fit is
because it has very strict types
typescript is a little bit trickier
because the types don't you have some
subtypes that don't really map like
number is not really that's not an
integer or float that's just a number so
you would need to have a maybe like a
superset of typescript in order to make
it possible to compile typescript you
need to add some new types to typescript
in order to make it possible to compile
typescript two webassembly efficiently
but we do think that that is possible
once we get this GC support in there we
think that you could have something like
typescript that compiles to web assembly
this brings up an interesting question
actually if you are compiling typescript
down to web assembly then there's some
things that the web assembly cannot
support
so is there a concept of shims or
something like that yes and so that's
the Wes and bind gen tool does give you
some of that shimming host bindings will
eventually replace part of that but yeah
for now you do have to have some of that
in place this is all you know it all
depends on the garbage collection
proposal which is still a bit of a ways
out so it's still all just talking about
it we haven't actually now there I
shouldn't say that there are people that
have experimented with compiling you'll
find a few projects that actually have
already attempted doing this kind of
compiling typescript to web assembly and
so you can see how they've done it but
as far as the actual design of how that
would eventually work we're probably
still a little bit further out from
having that nail down
I know scarlet jazz for instance have
looked at this I'm not sure how far
they've got but it's the kind of similar
sort of thing that you you were saying
about Elm because it's a statically
typed language how mature is the
technology if I write my application in
web assembly can I be sure that it will
work next week so they with the MVP they
basically made guarantees around
backwards compatibility now one of the
things that they're doing is that may
happen is if we do need to make changes
that could be backwards compatible
they put a version in the format so it
would be possible to version webassembly
if we absolutely need to but the hope is
that we won't need to that we can just
make sure that it continues to be
backwards compatible from the MVP date
which was last February through all the
way through the future up until 2030 if
Java has any experience together how
portable is it how much do I need to
care about my underlying system whether
or not it would be the browser or the
operating system that is one of the
major goals of pipe assembly is to make
it as portable as possible so ideally
you don't really need to care
ideally it would be possible to have a
VM on any kind of system that could then
take web assembly instructions and
convert them to whatever they need to be
okay
is there a concept of a polyfill the
first of all could you explain what
polyfill is sure so a polyfill is when
you basically fill in some functionality
that a browser doesn't have with code
that might run a little bit slower than
it would if it were implemented
implemented natively but so you know you
ship down a JavaScript library that can
do what the browser will need of ly do
at some point so that is what a polyfill
is you can kind of think of as I'm J s
as a polyfill for web assembly right now
if your browser doesn't support web
assembly what we recommend is you ship
down the azan J's version which will run
pretty fast still in Firefox and Chrome
in other other browsers didn't ever
optimize Assam Chasse I think that Apple
is one of the Safari is one of the ones
that didn't ever optimize as I'm Jas but
because it's just regular Jas it'll
still run it'll just be a little slow
okay is this a stupid idea but can you
wrote an WebP assembly code yes you can
run web assembly node and will actually
be luke Wagner and I'm Luke Wagner's one
of the people that pushed web sembly
forward he and I will be at the node
collaborators summit this summer
that's right around Jai has come for you
to talk about how you could use web
assembly with node I mean there's lots
of different options for how you could
do this we've talked with folks on the
note SAS project about how they could
use web assembly instead of compiling
their the underlying libsass to see
they're having it written in C and
compiling it so you could have these
native modules which are actually
running in web assembly instead of
native code that you have to compile and
then rebuild every single time you have
a new version but currently you can if
you're just using web assembly you can
use a note just like you can in
the browsers because it's nodes using
the v8 engine which has web assembly
support okay so it's using exactly the
same thing exactly okay so you could get
optimizations on a server back-end yeah
you could write web assembly code on the
server back-end that's for sure so
that's good if you were doing encryption
or compression or something like that
exactly yeah
okay so let's move on to security is it
to introduce security vulnerabilities
using web assembly it's so fortunately
you know this is one of the questions
that comes up a lot with web assembly
because people are worried that it's not
secure because they hear that it gives
you this low-level access to things like
memory but web assembly does some pretty
clever things to make sure that it has a
lot of the same security characteristics
as JavaScript so basically like I've
mentioned earlier it's using a lot of
the same code it's running in the same
VM so you have a lot of those same
protections so you can't access the file
system for instance exactly right you
context this is somebody else's mode
another modules memory exactly because
each one of these modules is using its
own memory object and one of the things
that web simply does is when you try to
access something in that memory object
when you try to pull it out or you try
to rewrite it it will do what's called
an array bounds check it will make sure
that you're staying within the bounds of
your object and if you're not it's going
to throw an exception
you said that I could access JavaScript
objects from a module can I pass in into
a module the object from another module
another web assembly module so could you
that that's the with the host bindings
proposal that would be the aim is that
you'd be able to pass these objects
around now currently you can't do that
you can only pass in functions okay but
eventually yes does the fact that you
you could be using web assembly intermix
of JavaScript make writing more secure
code harder because you're having having
to switch paradigms and
and I don't think that the paradigm you
know I don't think that writing in a
different language is really going to
change exactly your security mindsets
because a lot of the security concerns
that you have in JavaScript don't have
to do necessarily with JavaScript itself
but with the things that javascript is
doing so I think that you know a lot of
the same security mindset that you would
apply to JavaScript would also apply to
webassembly in the same way okay the
idea is that there are different
possible security vulnerabilities in
different languages so for instance you
never get a or you very rarely get a
buffer overrun in JavaScript whereas you
would a C or C++ potentially right so
there's buffer overflows those those do
still apply to webassembly basically you
within the memory object itself within
your application code you can to
potentially have those kinds of security
vulnerabilities but they're not going to
have such drastic effect as they would
if you were running the code like if you
had direct access to memory because
you're just in your own little sandbox I
don't your own little memory object so
if your your logic might break but
you're not going to then end up being
able to mess with the global object or
anything like that
okay okay how can I guard against binary
vulnerabilities so if I have a
JavaScript application I can look at the
source code for the JavaScript
application and it's quite easy to
analyze
as far as code is concerned so I can
look and see what see what's happening
whereas if it's a web assembly then it's
very hard to actually analyze and see if
there's anything any problems with it
how do I is there are there any
mechanisms for guarding against that
sort of thing
well at the engine level we do have some
verification one of the goals was to
make it so that the engine could verify
that no real shady stuff was happening
that the the code wasn't doing some very
malicious stuff of course you can still
have things that the engine wouldn't
recognize but that are malicious and
those are easier to tell when you are
looking at source that's true you can
actually go from source there are people
who are working on tools that go from
the assembly from web assembly back to
the source so you would basically then
be able to look at exactly the code that
is running in your browser somebody
recently did this with rust where they
were able to take this Gameboy emulator
in web assembly I don't think had even
been written and rust but they could
basically take the web assembly and
translate it back to rust okay so you
could take C++ translate it into web
assembly and then translate it back into
rust that's that was my impression from
what I saw I haven't dug into it myself
hey that sounds like a really good
solution for you know changing the
language of the compiling but do you do
any signing can we do signing of web
assembly there's nothing baked into the
web assembly spec that does that but to
the extent that you can do it for other
resources on the web you can do it okay
so future of web assembly where where is
web assembly going what's next so there
are some proposals that I've mentioned
throughout the podcast that we're really
focusing on in the web assembly
community group one of them is the
support for the es module API making it
possible to use web assembly modules in
regular JavaScript ES module grafts
another is this garbage collection that
was talking about but basically we're
trying to figure out what the users of
web assembly beyond games need because
we worked a lot with games in the early
development of web assembly but users
like ember like react what they would
actually need to make it easy to work
with web assembly in those code bases
and we're putting things into the spec
that will help with that so you were
talking about the VP the MVP is is
actually out now it's basically working
with games so what's the next MVP if
that makes sense
so I should make clear that's not just
working with games it is also like the
the source maps library that I talked
about that's working well I would say
that the next thing that you'll see
though is these frameworks you'll start
seeing things like or also languages
you'll start seeing things like Elm
compiling to webassembly and like I
mentioned before ember already has their
bytecode interpreter working in
webassembly so you'll see that landing
you'll start seeing this integration
more into the web applications that are
common to the web okay and what's the
time scale for all of this we're hoping
that we can have GC over this the course
of this year we're really gonna work on
it we're gonna focus on that we're
hoping that we can have it sooner rather
than later
of course GC is a really tricky problem
so it is hard to set any deadlines for
it but we are optimistic that we'll make
fast progress on it okay and in your
opinion would if I were to start on a
web application would I consider whether
web assembly I would say right now
you're still probably it's premature for
people that are just working on
day-to-day web applications to really be
digging into web assembly I'd say that
if you're a framework developer if
you're a library developer that for
those use cases it does make sense to
start exploring web assembly I would say
that for people that are just building
applications I maybe wait what you have
to learn another language RIS don't
that's true so you can get started on
learning that other language and then
once we have all of the other stuff in
place you'll have that language in your
back pocket okay
so CL C++ will rust yeah and I would
really recommend rust for a lot of
people I think that it gives you that
memory management security that we were
talking about before you know without as
much of the headache that you have in C
or C++ so for people that are web
developers it gives you a little bit of
an easier on ramp to that memory
management okay so this is starting to
wrap up now is there anything else I
should have asked you not that I can
think of
okay KITT how can listeners find out
more about this subject
so there is the web assembly community
group repo you can look there and find a
lot of the current design you can see
the proposals that we have going on I
also write a lot about web assembly on
the hacks blog for Mozilla you can take
a look at my code cartoon series I've
done a bunch of coke cartoons around
things like our streaming compiler what
makes web assembly fast how the memory
object works all of that kind of stuff
okay
how can people contribute I would say
contributing to projects that compile to
web assembly is actually a really great
place to start the rust webassembly
effort the rust web simply working group
they have a lot of work happening in the
the repos rust laying nursery slash rust
- wasum I'll send that to you you can
put it in the show notes ok but they
have a lot of projects for making sure
that rust can compile to webassembly
well and that that web assembly can work
well with JavaScript so getting involved
in something like that will really help
you get your feet wet with web assembly
and then you might be able to move on to
actually contributing to the community
group ok cool
well thank you very much for joining us
today Lynne thank you so much for having
me this is Matthew Farwell for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
you can also email us a team at SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening